Administration Department: Commissioner's Office:
Minnesota Historical Society
Hiniker (James J.) and Hale (Sandra J.) files.
1966-2004 (bulk 1979-1991).
Minnesota Historical Society
Minnesota. Dept. of Administration. Commissioner's Office.
Files of Commissioners James J. Hiniker (1979-1983) and Sandra J. Hale (1983-1991).
19.7 cu. ft. (20 boxes and 1 partial box).
SCOPE AND CONTENTS
The chronological files contain copies of outgoing letters, memoranda, and related materials mainly with other departmental personnel, state and local officials, legislators, and the general public. They deal with a variety of topics concerning the department's responsibility for the day to day management of the executive branch of state government, including personnel matters, legislation, the management of state land and institutions, and the construction and maintenance of state buildings. The letters in Hiniker's files are numbered sequentially. Hale's files include an alphabetical index.
The Hiniker/Hale subject files focus on the operations of the department's building code, building construction, energy conservation, management analysis, motor pool, organization and methods, personnel, plant management, printing and mailing services, telecommunications, procurement, and real estate management divisions, information services bureau, and data privacy unit, as well as relations with the departments of employee relations, finance, public welfare, and transportation, the governor's office, and various state correctional and educational institutions. They also contain staff meeting minutes and work plans.
The Hale subject files cover many of the issues and relationships found in the previous set, along with such topics as handicapped persons, the Minnesota History Center, materials management, and the Strive Toward Excellence in Performance [STEP] program, and relations with the Capitol Area Architectural and Planning Board, Governor's Residence Council, Loaned Executive Action Program, Minnesota Veterans' Home, the Energy and Economic Development Department, Legislative Auditor, Office of Volunteer Services, and State Arts Board. There are also copies of her speeches and files documenting her Executive Council service and post-commissioner work with Enterprise Management International.
ARRANGEMENT
The chronological files are arranged first by correspondent; thereunder chronologically.
These documents are arranged into the following sections:
Hiniker chronological files, 1979-1982
Hale chronological files, 1983-1987
Hiniker/Hale subject files, 1966-1987
Hale subject files, 1972-2004
CATALOG HEADINGS
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Minnesota Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics should search the catalog using these headings.
Topics:
Administrative law -- Minnesota.; Building laws -- Minnesota.; Correctional institutions -- Minnesota.; Education, Higher -- Minnesota.; Energy policy -- Minnesota.; Government publications -- Minnesota.; Government vehicles -- Minnesota.; Materials management -- Minnesota.; People with disabilities -- Minnesota.; Privacy, Right of -- Minnesota.; Public buildings -- Minnesota.; Public institutions -- Minnesota.; Public lands -- Minnesota.; Telecommunication policy -- Minnesota.
Persons:
Hale, Sandra J.; Hiniker, James J.
Organizations:
Governor's Residence Council (Minn.).; Minnesota History Center (Saint Paul, Minn.).; Minnesota Office on Volunteer Services.; Minnesota State Arts Board.; Minnesota Veterans Home (Minneapolis, Minn.).; Minnesota. Dept. of Employee Relations.; Minnesota. Dept. of Finance.; Minnesota. Dept. of Public Welfare.; Minnesota. Dept. of Transportation.; Minnesota. Dept. of Administration. Information Services Bureau.; Minnesota. Capitol Area Architectural and Planning Board.; Minnesota. Dept. of Energy and Economic Development.; Minnesota. Executive Council.; Minnesota. Governor's Loaned Executives Action Program.; Minnesota. Legislature. Office of the Legislative Auditor.; Minnesota. Office of the Governor.; Strive Toward Excellence in Performance (Program: Minn.).
Places:
Minnesota -- Executive departments -- Management.; Minnesota -- Personnel management.
Functions:
Supervising.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
Accession Information:
Accession numbers: 991-164; 997-37; 998-18; 999-37; 2001-48; 2004-24; 2004-54; 2005-59; 2012-9
DETAILED DESCRIPTION
- Hiniker chronological files, 1979-1982
  - Nos. 1-1979, March 1979-September 1982.; 19 folders.
- Hale chronological files, 1983-1987
  - Alphabetical index, 1983-1987.
  - 1983-1985., 18 folders.
- Hiniker/Hale subject files, 1966-1987
  - Affirmative Action Committee:
    - Minutes, 1979-1981.
    - Reports, 1979-1981.
    - Correspondence, 1979-1983.
  - Brainerd DNR facility, 1978.
    Program and preliminary schematic design study.
  - Building Code Division, 1981-1983.; 2 folders.
  - Building Construction Division, 1979-1983.; 5 folders.
  - Capitol Area Architectural and Planning Board, 1980-1981.
  - Capitol Area parking, November 1983.
  - Capitol Improvement Plan, 1979-June 1983.; 2 folders.
  - Cass Gilbert Park, 1980.
  - C.E.T.A., April 1979-January 1980.
  - Commuter Van Program:
    - 1980-1983.
    - Program analysis, March 18, 1982.
  - Constituent mail, 1983-1984.; 2 folders.
  - Copeland, William C.: Refinancing and Reorganizing Human Services: Inter-Agency Net Budgeting and Other Fiscal Incentives, March 4, 1981.
  - Computer system, installation of new, July-September 1983.
  - Cost savings program, 1978, 1983.
  - County Financial and Reporting System [COFARS], 1978-1980.
  - Crime Control Planning Board: Minnesota Justice System Improvement Study-Research Design, August 1980.
  - Data Privacy Unit, March 1977-1983.; 3 folders.
  - Duluth Government Center, 1979-1983.
  - Electricity Board, 1978-1982.
  - Employee Relations Department, 1979-1984.; 3 folders.
  - Energy Conservation Division, 1979-1983.; 3 folders.
  - Energy Coordination Task Force, 1983.
  - Energy Department, 1979-1983.
    Includes Analysis of Staffing Needs at Minnesota Energy Agency, February 27, 1980.
  - Energy, miscellaneous, 1979-1984.
  - ETA Super Computer, 1983.
  - Executive Claims Committee, 1979.
  - Fergus Falls State Hospital, 1979-1983.
  - Film, Video, and Graphic Arts Committee, 1983-1984.
  - Finance Department:
    - Statewide Financial Management Study (Price Waterhouse), 1979.; 2 folders.
    - 1977-1983., 3 folders.
  - Financial Management Information Task Force, 1979-1981.
  - Freeze, Executive Order 83-3, 1983.
  - Gasoline conservation, 1976, 1979-1985.
  - Goff Report, 1979-1982.
    Includes Governor's Task Force on Waste and Mismanagement Report, January 1979.
  - Governor's Office (transition), November 1978-January 1979.
  - Governor's Office (Quie), 1978-1982.; 3 folders.
  - Governor's Office (Perpich), 1983.; 3 folders.
  - Governor's Task Force to Reduce State Mandates on Local Governments, 1982.; 2 folders.
  - Health Care Study Task Force:
    - Miscellaneous., 2 folders.
    - May-December 1981., 2 folders.
    - May-December 1981., 1 folder.
    - Final report, December 1981.
  - Health and Public Welfare merger, 1983.
  - Human Rights Department, 1979-1984.
    Includes operational analysis, January 24, 1984.
  - Information Services Bureau:
    - Audit, 1976-1984.; 2 folders.
    - Friday Report, 1979-1982.
    - Information Services newsletter, 1980-1982.
    - Program evaluation, February 1980.
    - Program evaluation, March 1980.
    - State Information System Advisory Council, 1979-1982.
    - Systems Advisory Committee, 1979-1983.
    - User Advisory Council, 1983-1984.
    - General information, 1979-1984.
      - 5 folders.
      - 2 folders.
  - Intergovernmental Information Systems Advisory Council, 1984.
  - Interstate Cooperation Commission, 1977-1980.
  - Inver Hills Community College, September 1983.
  - Investment Board, 1979-1981.
  - Iron Range Resources and Rehabilitation Board: Fens Bog Pilot Project Plan, 1983.
  - Job sharing, 1979-1980.
  - Labor Relations Department, 1979-1982.; 4 folders.
  - Land Management Information Center, 1983.
  - Land, State owned, 1980-1983.
  - Legislation, 1980-1984.; 4 folders.
  - Legislative Commission to Review Administrative Rules, 1980-1984.
  - Legislative Reference Library, 1979-1983.
  - Licensing, Statewide, 1979-1982.
  - Management Advisory Council:
    - 1983-1984.
    - Minutes, 1983-1984.
  - Management Analysis Division:
    - 1975-1983., 2 folders.
    - Monthly status reports, 1980-1982.
  - Management by Objective:
    - 1966-1975.
    - Overheads, 1974.
  - Management Services Division, 1977.
  - Manager's meetings, 1980-1982.
  - Mankato State University, 1979-1982.
  - Metric system, 1980.
  - Metropolitan Transit Commission, 1979-1982.
  - Metropolitan Waste Control Commission, 1979-1982.
  - Military Affairs, 1979-1983.
  - Minnesota Benefit Association, 1980.
  - Minnesota Educational Computing Consortium, 1980-1983.
  - Minnesota Emergency Employment Development Act, 1983.
  - Minnesota Occupational Information System Board, 1979.
  - Minnesota Office on Volunteer Services:
    - 1979-1984., 2 folders.
    - Pilot Community Manual, December 1982.
  - Minnesota Tax Study Commission, 1983-1984.
  - Minnesota Washington Office, 1983.
  - Model for Economic Analysis Forecasts, Input/Output Models, 1974-1976.; 2 folders.
  - Moorhead State University, 1979-1983.
  - Motor Pool Division, 1979-1983.; 3 folders.
  - Natural Resources Department, 1979-1984.
  - Office Equipment Repair and Rental Section: Procurement Division: Investigation report and closing of section, 1980-1983.
  - Organization and Methods Division, 1969-1979.; 3 folders.
  - Personnel Services Division:
    - 1978-1984.
    - Activity reports, 1981-1983.
  - Plant Management Division:
    - Monthly reports, 1982-1984.
    - 1979-1982., 2 folders.
    - 1983-1984., 2 folders.
  - Printing Advisory Committee, 1979-1980.
  - Printing and Mailing Services Division:
    - 1979-1983., 2 folders.
    - Publications., 9 items in 1 folder.
      - Examination of Minnesota's Printing and Duplicating Operations, Council of State Governments, September 1979.
      - Presentation of Minnesota Copy Center Concept, October 12, 1979.
      - Publications and General Services Division Report, December 3, 1980.
      - Printing and Mailing Services Report, January 27, 1981.
      - Rate Setting Approach, FY1982.
      - PLO Newsletter, November. 16, 1979 and April 1980.
      - Type (manual), circa 1980.
      - PM Impressions, March and December 1981, November 1982.
      - Minnesota Communicator- Minnesota Chapter National Association of Government Communicators, March-May 1981.
  - Procurement Division:
    - Authority for local purchases, 1982.
    - Implementation book, 1984.
    - 1979-1984., 6 folders.
    - Minnesota Small Business Procurement Program for Socially or Economically Disadvantaged Vendors, Annual reports, FY1982-1983.
    - Procurement News, 1980.
    - Activity reports, 1981-1982.
  - Public Welfare Department, 1979-1984.; 2 folders.
  - Quality Circles, 1983.
  - Real Estate Management Division:
    - 1979-1981., 3 folders.
    - 1982-1987., 4 folders.
  - Reduction of staff, 1979-1983.
  - Resource Conservation and Recovery, 1979-1984.
  - Rochester State Hospital, 1981-1984.
  - Rochester State Hospital Task Force, 1982.
  - Saint Peter State Hospital, 1979-1983.
  - Service Assistance Office, 1980.
  - Small Business Procurement Act:
    - Annual report, 1978.
    - 1979-1987., 3 folders.
    - Evaluation of Set-Aside Program, February 16, 1982.
  - Staff meeting minutes:
    - 1979-1981., 5 folders.
    - 1982-1984., 4 folders.
  - State Band, 1984-1986.
  - State Ceremonial Building (Governor's Mansion), 1978-1983.
  - State Ceremonial House Committee, 1978-1983.; 3 folders.
  - State Employees, Inc., 1980.
  - State Facilities Master Planning Process, 1980.
  - State Planning Agency, 1981-1984.; 2 folders.
  - State Register Division, 1979-1984.
  - Stillwater State Prison/Oak Park Heights Correctional Facility:
    - 1978-1981., 2 folders.
    - 1981-1983., 1 folder.
  - Super Computer Institute, 1984.
  - Telecommunications, 911:
    - Report to the Legislature, 1979-1981, 1983.; 2 folders.
    - 1979-1982., 3 folders.
  - Telecommunications Department:
    - Conference, February 6-7, 1984.
    - 1977-1984., 4 folders.
  - Transportation Department:
    - 1979-1984.
    - Recommendations for MnDot Reorganization, June 1979.
    - Management Study of MnDot Maintenance Operations Management Analysis Division, February 1983.
  - Unions, 1980-1983.
  - University of Minnesota, 1979-1981.
  - User Council on Office Systems, 1979-1983.
  - Veterans Affairs Department, 1979-1984.
  - Volunteer for Minnesota:
    - Kick-Off Conference, September 30, 1982.
    - Correspondence, 1981-1982.
    - Agenda packets, 1982.
    - VFM Pilot training, 1982.
    - Miscellaneous, 1982.
  - Waste-recycling, 1980-1985.
  - Winona State University, August 1983.
  - Work plans, FY1983.; 2 folders.
  - Zoo, Board consultants, 1973-1974.
  - Zoo (Minnesota Zoological Garden), 1979-1984.
- Hale subject files, 1972-2004
  - Administration personnel, 1985-1990.
  - Administrative files, circa 1980-1993.; 4 folders.
    Includes conference and seminar outlines and materials, strategic planning, correspondence, brochures, and newsletters relating to her work as Commissioner and with the State Arts Board and Enterprise Management, International.
  - Administrative goals and accomplishments, 1983-1990.
    Includes action plans, statement of values, current projects, mission statements and office memorandum.
  - Archives, 1978-1979.
  - Air pollution, 1983-1984.
  - Artificial intelligence, 1990.
  - Biography, circa 1970s-1990s.
    Includes professional accomplishments, employment history, resumes, references, and certificates of awards.
  - Blue Ribbon Committee on Information Policies, 1985-1987.
  - Building codes and standards, 1983-1985.
  - Building Fund, 1979-1982.
  - CAAPB [Capitol Area Architectural and Planning Board], 1982-1990.; 4 folders.
  - Cable communications, 1979-1985.; 2 folders.
  - Capitol budget, 1987.
  - Capitol Mall, 1986-1987.
  - Capitol restoration, 1983-1990.
  - Commissioner’s feedback sessions, 1984-1989.
  - Contracts management, 1979-1988.
  - Correspondence, 1980s-2004.
    Correspondence sent and received to government officials, private businesses, nonprofit administrators, general public and personal congratulatory notes.
    - 1 folder.
    - 6 folders.
  - Data privacy, 1989-1990.
  - Defining the Elephant (Strategic Management Plan for 1989-1990), October-November 1988.
  - Democratic Leadership Council, 1990.
  - Designer Selection Board, 1981-1990.
  - Economic Development Department, 1979-1987.
  - Economic Security Department, 1979-1985.
  - Employee Relations Department, 1984-1988.
  - Enterprise management, 1990.
  - Energy and Economic Development, 1983-1987.; 2 folders.
  - Energy/environment, 1990.
  - Executive Council:
    - Breckenridge fire request, 1977.
    - Buhl coal problem, 1972.
    - Herbicide problem, 1982.
  - Executive Management Subcabinet, 1983-1990.; 8 folders.
  - Executive Orders, 1983-1989.; 2 folders.
  - Executive Team, 1989-1990.
  - Exposing good government, 1986.
  - Farm mediation files, 1986-1991.; 4 folders.
    Approved and closed cases, background material, and list reports.
  - Finance Department, 1983-1989.; 4 folders.
  - Gorbachev Maxwell Institute of Technology, 1990.
  - Gorbachev visit, 1990.; 2 folders.
  - Governor Perpich:
    - 1983-1990., 2 folders.
    - Business Day visit, 1989.
    - Proposed Budget, 1983-1985.
    - Minnesota/Wisconsin Summit in Duluth, 1990.
    - State of the State, 1983-1989.
  - Governor’s Residence Council, 1983-1989.; 6 folders.
  - Grace Commission, 1984-1985.
  - Greater Minnesota Corporation, 1987-1990.
  - Handicapped, 1978-1989.; 2 folders.
  - Health Department, 1979-1988.
  - [Minnesota] History Center, 1985-1990.; 3 folders.
  - Hospitals study, 1984.
  - Information Policy Council, 1985-1988.
  - Information Services Bureau, 1980-1988.; 3 folders.
  - Information systems development, 1987-1989.
  - Inventory Management Division, 1979-1987.
  - International Leadership Center, 1986-1990.
  - Legislative Auditor, 1979-1983.; 2 folders.
  - Legislative correspondence, 1981-1988.
  - Letter from Governor Rudy Perpich, January 3, 1991.
  - Loaned Executive Action Program, 1973-1987.; 2 folders.
  - Management, 1987-1990.
  - Management Advisory Council, 1984-1989.; 2 folders.
  - Managing internal service activities, undated, 1989.
  - Materials management, 1983-1990.; 2 folders.
  - Materials Management-Vendor Quality Management, 1986.
  - Mechanic Arts, 1980-1984.
  - Minnesota Business Partnership, 1983-1989.
  - Minnesota Office of Volunteer Services, 1983-1990.; 2 folders.
  - Minnesota Veterans’ Home, 1984-1989.; 2 folders.
  - News clippings, 1970-2004.; 11 folders.
    Includes newspaper and newsletter clippings related to Commissioner Hale and the Administration Department and her various community roles.
  - Panza Art Concourse, 1987-1988.; 2 folders.
  - Photographs, undated.
    Photographs of Commissioner Hale and unidentified persons.
  - Plant Management, 1983-1990.; 2 folders.
  - Public Safety Department, 1980-1988.; 2 folders.
  - Publications, circa 1970s-1990s.; 3 folders.
    Various magazine and journal publications which include an article written by or about Sandra Hale.
  - Records Center, 1984-1988.
  - Records management, 1978-1980.
  - Small Business Procurement Advisory Council [SBAC], 1986-1990.
  - Speech background material, circa 1980s-1990s.; 2 folders.
  - Speeches, 1984-1995.; 5 folders.
    Speeches given nationally and internationally as Commissioner and as President of Enterprise Management at conferences, seminars and commencements.
  - State Arts Board, 1983-1991.; 2 folders.
  - State Hospital (Rochester), 1981-1982.
  - State Hospital Study, 1984.
  - State Hospital System, The Future of, 1982-1984.
  - State Planning Agency, 1988-1991.
  - STEP [Strive Toward Excellence in Performance], 1983-1991.
    STEP, a tool for improving the quality, quantity and cost effectiveness of state government services, was launched in the spring of 1985 by Governor Perpich and ended in 1991 when Governor Carlson created the Commission on Reform and Efficiency [CORE]. Included are STEP hypotheses, projects, program highlights, newsletter and newspaper clippings.
    - 1 folder.
    - 5 folders.
  - Telecommunications, 1983-1989.; 6 folders.
  - Transition Team [Governor’s Office], 1990.